We all are expecting something great to happen and the happening that has to take place has
我們都在期待某些偉大的事件發生，而那些必須發生的事件
been already described in all the scriptures.
早已在所有經典中被描述。
But somehow we are misled by other people who have a better way of manifesting their
但不知何故，我們被其他善於展現自身風格的人們所誤導，
own style and we get so confused because this is the time of great confusion.
以致感到無比困惑，因為這本就是個充滿混亂的時代。
Without the confusion evolution cannot take place.
沒有混亂，進化就無法發生。
Unless and until people are confused they will never try to aspire for something higher.
除非人們感到困惑，否則他們永遠不會渴望更高的境界。
If you see in the animal stage also, there was a confusion for the fishes to come out,
縱觀動物的進化歷程，魚類也經歷了一段困惑期，
and that confusion made one or two to lead the rest of them and that’s how they could
而正是這種困惑促使一兩隻帶頭，其他跟隨，牠們才能成功上岸
crawl onto this Mother Earth with confidence.
帶著自信在這片大地母親上爬行。
So the areas started changing gradually, that, from Mother Earth then they started looking
它們的領域開始逐漸發生變化，從大地母親轉向
towards the sky.
逐漸延伸到天空。
And the evolution went on like this till the human beings were created.
這樣的演化持續進行，直至人類被創造出來。演化就這樣持續進行，直到人類的出現。
Now, all these areas are within ourselves.
如今，這些領域全都存在於我們自身之中。
These are all the elements into which we had to probe into: we had to find about them.
這些皆是我們必須探究的要素：我們必須找出它們的真相。
And through this evolution we have been able to look into these, to fathom them, to find
透過這演化過程，我們得以窺探這些元素，洞悉其本質，並運用智慧
out their nature through our intelligence.
發掘它們的真實樣貌。
So we reached this point where we could understand the elements, we could understand their use
於是我們來到這個階段，不僅能理解這些元素，還能了解它們的用途
for our purpose.
以符合我們的需求。
So far so good.
目前為止一切順利。
But that’s not the end.
但這還不是終點。
That’s not the end of our evolution.
這並非我們進化的終點。
If it was then there would have been no more search, there would have been no more seeking,
若真如此，便不會再有探索、不會再有追尋，
people would have been happy, would have been satisfied, but that’s not so.
人們理應感到快樂、感到滿足，但事實卻非如此。
So there has to be something more that we have to achieve.
所以必定還有我們必須實現的更高境界。
At this time of great confusion we have certain lamp posts, we can say, or beacons, to guide
在這混亂不堪的時刻，我們可以說有幾盞明燈，或是燈塔，指引著我們
us and these beacons are all the scriptures.
而這些燈塔就是所有的經典。
Now these scriptures are also so much being misused and misrepresented and explained in
然而現在這些經典也經常被誤用、曲解，以如此荒謬的方式詮釋，
such a funny way and everything made into a money-making proposition, that it adds to
甚至把一切都變成了牟利的買賣，這只會讓情況更加惡化
the confusion more.
更加困惑了。
So you get much more confused and confused and confused.
所以你會越來越困惑，越來越糊塗。
Imagine the light that has to show your path becomes an illusion: how are you to find your
想像那本該引導你前進的光芒，其實只是幻覺：你要如何找到你的
path then.
道路呢。
But this is the pastime of human beings, you can’t help it.
但這就是人類的通病，你無可奈何。
You give them everything and they can convert it into a confusion.
你給他們一切，他們卻能把所有都轉化為一團混亂。
You can see the results of these in our politicians, in our economists, our psychologists: all
從我們的政治人物、經濟學家、心理學家身上都能看到這些結果：
of them seem to be quite confused, and they don’t know what the other person is saying,
他們似乎都相當困惑，而且根本聽不懂別人在說什麼。
what they are saying.
他們所說的話。
And they cannot relate it to something absolute.
而他們無法將其與某種絕對的事物聯繫起來。
So we have to find out that absolute point where this confusion drops out.
因此，我們必須找出那個讓這種困惑消失的絕對點。
At this level only you can find it out, at this level only it can be given, at this level
只有在這個階段，你才能找到它，只有在這個階段，它才能被賦予，也只有在這個階段，
only that will manifest.
它才會顯現。
Before this, at any other stage it is impossible.
在此之前，在其他任何階段都是不可能的。
It was impossible and it is impossible.
過去不可能，就是也不可能。
So at human stage only it is going to manifest.
只有在人類階段才會顯現。
But human beings also must know that they have some drawbacks compared to other stages.
然而人類也必須認知到，相較於其他階段，他們確實存在某些缺陷。
At the animal stage or even earlier stages you can say: at the element stage.
在動物階段，甚至更早的階段，你可以說：在元素階段。
Elements don’t have to think.
元素無需思考。
They don’t have any choice.
它們沒有任何選擇。
They don’t have to bother about anything.
他們不必為任何事煩心。
They just exist.
他們只是存在著。
They are not aware of anything; they are just existing with whatever are their qualities:
他們對任何事都毫無覺知；只是帶著各自的特質存在著：
say hydrogen is hydrogen, oxygen is oxygen.
比如說氫就是氫，氧就是氧。
They are bound by different valencies and different qualities and their chemical compounds
它們透過不同的化合價、不同的性質、化學組成以及物理性質而結合在一起
and their physical powers by which they act, react and exist.
這些性質決定了它們如何行動、反應和存在。
Then when the life started itself, at that time also, life was guided, very much by nature.
接著當生命開始時，在那個時候，生命也很大程度地受到自然的指引。
The evolution was very much controlled by nature.
進化的過程在很大程度上是由自然所控制的。
I’ll give you an example of that.
我給你舉個例子。
A gentleman who has written a very nice book – I would not give you the name because
有位先生寫了一本非常棒的書——我就不告訴你書名了因為
you will immediately buy that book and start reading the whole thing – but he was experimenting
你會立刻去買那本書然後開始從頭讀起——他當時在洛杉磯（靠近海邊）
with some oysters and he had them first in Los Angeles where the sea was.
做牡蠣實驗。
And he found out that when the tide was low these shells used to open themselves up, the
他發現，退潮時牡蠣殼會自然打開，
oysters, and when it was high tide they would close down because the water should not run
而當漲潮時它們會閉合，因為海水不該流
into them.
進它們體內。
And you know that the tide time is bound everywhere: anybody can calculate it sitting down here
而你也知道潮汐時間到處都是固定的：任何人都可以坐在這裡計算出來
what is the tide in Falkland.
福克蘭群島的潮汐時間
So he removed those shells from there, brought them to Ohio which is very far away and there
於是他把那些貝殼從那裡移走，帶到了非常遙遠的俄亥俄州
is no sea and he put them down there and they were opening at the same time.
那裡沒有海洋，他將貝殼放在那裡，牠們仍會同時開合。
Now see: the time changes according to the moon, so the water was acting according to
現在請注意：時間會隨月亮變化，所以水也是根據（潮汐）
the moon and these oysters were also acting according to the moon.
月亮和這些牡蠣同樣遵循著月亮的節奏行事。
But when the time changed, they came to Ohio, still they had that habit and they were opening.
當時間改變，他們來到了俄亥俄州，仍然保持原來的生長規律，並繼續開殼
But suddenly they changed and they took to the timing which would happen if the sea was
但他們突然改變了，開始適應俄亥俄州若有海才會出現的生長規律！
there in Ohio!
開始適應俄亥俄州若有海才會出現的生長規律！
So they were so much bound still by nature.
因此他們仍深受自然所束縛
Nature controls them, and up to a great point, nature even controlled human beings.
大自然控制著它們，在很大程度上，大自然甚至控制著人類。
But in the animal stage one has to know that, to find out the difference between an animal
但在動物階段須知的是，要明瞭動物
and a vegetable, what happened was, first the cellular wall was doubled.
與植物間的差異，關鍵在於細胞壁首度出現了雙層結構
So element was first put into a cell to make a vegetable and the vegetable was given a
也就是說，最初進入細胞的元素是為了形成植物，而這植物又被賦予了
double wall to make it an animal.
雙層細胞壁，從而形成了動物。
Now [an] animal that has become a human being has a triple bond, that’s why is the confusion.
如今，一個由動物演化而來的人類具有三重束縛，這就是困惑的根源。
That we call as ‘human freedom’: that we are free to do what we like: “What’s
我們稱之為「人類自由」：我們可以自由做自己想做的事：
wrong?”
「這樣有什麼不對？」
Correct!
沒錯！
I mean if somebody wants to commit suicide, what’s wrong?
我是說如果有人想自殺，那有什麼不對？
Somebody wants to kill his father, what’s wrong?
有人想殺他老爸，有什麼不對？
I mean laws according to many people is all artificial, man-made — is correct.
我的意思是，很多人都認為法律完全是人造的、人為制定的——沒錯。
So, what’s wrong?
那麼，問題出在哪裡？
So we were bound thrice.
我們被三重束縛。
The third binding came when, as human beings, we started acting, creating our ego as a by-product
第三重束縛發生在當作為人類，我們開始行動，並將自我意識作為副產物創造出來時。
of that action, physical and mental.
關於這一行為，包括生理和心理層面。
We developed ourselves into an egg.
我們將自身發展成了一顆蛋。
We became just like eggs and this egg had three shells.
我們變得如同蛋一般，而這顆蛋擁有三層殼。
First one of the human shell, second of the animal, and third that of the vegetables and
第一層是人類的外殼，第二層是動物的，第三層則是植物與蔬菜的。
inside that were all the elements.
裡面包含所有元素。
That’s how we are made.
這就是我們的構成方式。
But for what?
但這是為了什麼？
Why?
為什麼？
Why this freedom was given to us?
為何我們被賦予這份自由？
To get us confused?
讓我們感到困惑嗎？
Because we had to go to a higher evolutionary state, and that higher evolutionary state
因為我們必須進化到更高的層次，而那個更高的進化境界
has to give us complete freedom from all these three bondages: the vegetable bondage which
必須使我們完全擺脫這三種束縛：植物的束縛
makes you stick to one place, the animal bondage where you cannot think, and human bondage
讓你困在原地，動物性的束縛，讓你無法思考，以及人類的束縛
where you think.
讓你思考。
Man can’t live without thinking: it’s a bondage.
人類無法不思考：這也是一種束縛。
We can’t get out of it.
我們無法擺脫它。
Like horns it grows into your head.
如同角一般長進你的腦袋裡。
You can’t stop it you know.
你明白的，無法阻止它。
Even if you cut your throat you cannot stop it, some people say – it’s surprising.
有人說——即便割斷喉嚨也無法阻止，真是令人驚訝。
It’s so bad, it’s such a bondage in us.
它是如此糟糕，如此束縛著我們。
All the time we think, think, think.
我們無時無刻都在思考，思考，思考。。
This is the third bondage: of human being.
這就是人類的第三種束縛。
But what happens with this when this bondage is broken?
但當這種束縛被打破時會發生什麼？
Light comes in, through the light.
光隨即透過光明降臨。
And this light gives you enlightenment in all the three prisons into which you are imprisoned;
這道光為你帶來啟迪，照亮你所受困的三重牢獄；
and you get a complete integration into all these different bondages within you and you
你將完全融入這些內在的各種束縛之中
start seeing the absolute truth: that all this is bound by one thread.
並開始看見絕對真理：這一切都被同一條線索所繫。
All these elements, all these vegetables, animals, human beings are bound by one thread.
所有這些元素、植物、動物、人類，皆由同一條線索所維繫。
And when you start seeing that thread as a witness, you start seeing the play of all
當你開始以觀察者的身份看見那條線索時，你便會看見所有
these elements, of all these bondages — beautifully.
這些元素的運作，所有這些束縛——美妙地呈現。
But there’s a very great difference between the other evolution and the evolution of man
但在這個階段，其他生物的進化與人類的進化
at this stage.
存在著極大的差異。
It’s a very great difference I think, which very few people realise: that before the evolution
我認為這其中有很大的差別，但鮮少有人意識到：在進化到人類階段之前，
up to human stage, you are not aware of it and you can’t do anything about it at all.
你對此毫無覺察，也完全無法採取任何行動。
Supposing a seed evolves into a better fruit — it doesn’t have to do anything about
就像一顆種子進化成更好的果實——它本身無需採取任何行動，
it, somebody else has to do.
這件事需要由其他存在來完成。
If you sprout a seed then you have to look after it throughout.
若你種下一顆種子，就必須一路照料它。
Sprout the seed then take the seedlings, put them right somewhere then let them grow into
播種後取得幼苗，將其安置妥當，讓它們茁壯成長為
a tree, then you have to prune the tree.
一棵樹後，還得修剪枝葉。
Whatever you have to do, you have to do all the time, you have to look after the tree.
無論要做什麼，都得持續不斷，必須好好照料這棵樹。
But after this evolution, this jumping, this happening, when you become the Self, you have
但在經歷了這段進化、這番躍遷、這個轉變之後，當你成為真我時，你就必須
to do something about it: you have to.
採取行動：你別無選擇。
Because you become the master of your being.
因為你已成為自身生命的主宰。
It is you who has to work it out.
唯有你能完成這項修行。
In Sahaja Yoga there are many people who get Realisation: it’s very easy.
在霎哈嘉瑜伽中，有許多人獲得自覺：這非常容易。
The confusion is so great that people want to come out of it, [so] they get it.
困惑如此之大，以至於人們想要從中解脫，[因此]他們得到了它。
But again they are drawn back into it because that time which is so important, the intermediary
但他們再次被拉回其中，因為那個如此重要的時刻，即中間
time, where you have to stick on to that area, to that new dimension of collective consciousness,
時刻，你必須堅持在那個領域，那個集體意識的新維度，
your willpower doesn’t act, and that is the time you require this will power.
你的意志力卻無法發揮作用，而這正是最需要你的意志力的時候。
Already you are exhausted.
你卻已精疲力竭了。
So many are exhausted because of seeking, because of worrying, because of thinking,
太多人因為追求、因為憂慮、因為思考而精疲力竭，
wrong seeking, gurus, this that.
錯誤的追求、假導師、這個那個。
All kinds of exhaustions are there: family life, married life.
各式各樣的疲憊都存在著：家庭生活、婚姻生活。
Every sort of problem that you have faced, you have already exhausted your willpower.
你所面臨的每一種問題，都已經耗盡了你的意志力。
And when even you get Realised, you have the cup, but you have no strength to lift, within
即使當你獲得了自覺，你手中握著那隻金杯，卻沒有力氣舉起，
yourself, to raise it to your mouth and to enjoy the nectar of your Realisation.
無法將其舉到嘴邊，享受自覺後的甘露。
More so in places that are supposed to be developed.
尤其是在那些已開發國家。
In developing that part of your systems you have exhausted yourself much more.
在開發系統的這部分時，你真的耗盡了太多精力。
I mean it was all right up to a point, but when human beings know something, they’ll
我的意思是，在某種程度上發展是可以接受的，但只要人類一旦掌握某些事物，
go to the extreme end of everything.
他們就會將一切推向極端。
Now, if you know electricity, then everything must work on electricity, your lift will work
現在，如果你懂電，那麼所有東西都必須靠電運作，你的電梯會靠電運轉
on electricity, this will work on electricity, now computers have come, all right.
電腦會靠電運作，現在電腦已經出現了，好吧。
Now they will make human beings into electrical electrodes!
現在他們要把人類變成電極！
I don’t know what they’re going to make out of that.
我不知道他們到底想搞出什麼名堂。
I mean, going to that extent.
我的意思是，做到那種程度。
But then electricity fails — finished!
但電力突然失效了——全完了！
Now petrol has started — use petrol as much as you like, all right.
現在汽油開始了——你想用多少汽油就用多少，好吧。
Now petrol is getting exhausted.
現在汽油快要耗盡了。
So there’s a shock, future shock condition.
所以這是一種震驚，未來的震盪狀態。
In a trauma we sit.
我們處在一種創傷中。
In that confused state you are in a shocked state, “Oh God what’s going to happen
在那種困惑狀態下，你處於震驚狀態，「天啊，接下來會發生什麼事
to us?”
在我們身上？」
But why play into the hands of these things to that extent.
但為什麼要如此迎合這些元素呢？
The countries which are not so developed, we can say countries which are a little underdeveloped
那些發展程度不這麼高的國家，我們可以說是稍微落後的國家：
and developed: where a motor car runs and a bullock cart also runs.
那裡有汽車行駛，也有牛車行駛。
If the motor car fails they can use the oxes to run the motor cars, we call it ‘Ox Ford’.
如果汽車拋錨了，他們可以用牛來拉動汽車，我們稱之為「牛津」。
(laughter)
(笑聲)
So one can rely on something else, there is an alternative already available.
所以人們可以依靠其他替代方案，總是有替代方案。
But when you cut out all the alternatives, then how can you find out an alternative.
但當你切斷了所有替代方案，又怎麼能找到其他選擇。
For example, now we’ve got calculators.
比方說，現在我們有了計算機。
I was amazed in the shop: they can’t count one, two, three, four, five.
我在店裡感到非常驚訝：他們竟然不會數一、二、三、四、五。
If they make mistakes in somewhere, if you tell them that, that’s a mistake, because
如果計算機算錯了，而你告訴他們那是錯的，
you know how to calculate, they say, “How can it be?
因為你知道怎麼計算，他們會說：「這怎麼可能？
The machine is not wrong."
機器不會出錯的。」
But your fingers were wrong somewhere.
但你的手指可能哪裡按錯了。
They have no alternatives left now.
他們現在沒有其他選擇了。
I mean they have to depend on the electricity.
我是說他們得靠電力運作。
They have to depend on petrol.
他們得仰賴石油能源。
You have to depend on all these elements.
必須依賴所有這些元素。
So if you find with a little detachment: we are already slaves of all these elements.
所以如果你稍微冷靜地思考一下，就會發現：我們早已成為所有這些元素的奴隸。
Instead of becoming free birds, we have become now slaves of this.
我們非但沒有成為自由的鳥兒，反倒淪為了這些事物的奴隸。
So we start finding out alternatives.
於是我們開始尋找替代方案。
Now what can alternatives we can have?
那我們還有什麼其他的選擇嗎？
We have lost all deftness to do any hand work.
我們已經完全失去了動手做事的靈巧度。
After some time I think people won’t be able to clean their dishes, they will need
我想再過一段時間，人們應該連自己的碗盤都無法清洗了，他們會需要
a machine.
一台機器。
As it is they can’t clean their clothes I think, they can’t comb their hair.
我認為他們現在連衣服都沒辦法洗，頭髮也沒辦法梳。
What’s going to happen?
接下來會怎樣？
You will need even a machine to feed you!
你甚至需要機器來餵你吃飯！
Going to that extent: when we go up to such a limit that we become absolute slaves.
到那種程度：當我們把自己逼到極限，就會徹底淪為奴隸。
The confusion is worse.
困惑感更加嚴重了。
But after Realisation the whole thing changes.
但自覺後整個情況都改變了。
All the priorities change, you become a different person.
所有優先順序都變了，你變成完全不同的人。
It’s a tremendous change that comes within you.
這是一個發生在你內在的巨大轉變。
But to appreciate it, to understand it and use it, you have to stabilise yourself because
但要欣賞它、理解它並運用它，你必須先穩定自己。
you are still shaking.
因為你還在搖擺不定。
And it’s very easy to go back to the life which you have lead so far.
而且很容易地回到你過去的生活方式。
We have had people coming from all works of life.
各行各業的人來我們這裡。
We had bureaucrats.
我們這裡有官僚。
We had people who were hippies.
我們這裡有嬉皮士。
They must belong to some club: “Are you a communist or a socialist?”
他們都必須附屬於某個圈子：「你是共產主義者還是社會主義者？」
Like when I came here, they asked me, “What is your politics?”
就像我來的時候，他們問我：「你的政治立場是什麼？」
I looked at them.
我看著他們。
I said, “Which one?”
我問：「哪一個？」
They said, “I mean what politics we have.
他們說：「我是說我們的政治立場。
What is yours?”
那你的呢？」
I said, “I don’t know."
我說：「我不知道。」
Quite confused you see.
你看，我當時很困惑。
I was quite confused, because I had no politics at all.
我當時很困惑，因為我對政治一竅不通。
There’s only one politics for me, that is the politics of the Divine, of God: where
對我來說，政治只有一種，那就是神聖的政治，上帝的政治：在那裡
He plays His tricks on all human beings; I see that every day.
祂對所有人類施展祂的伎倆；我每天都能看見。
They don’t know, but He’s playing tricks on everyone: on nations, on human beings,
他們不知道，但祂正在對每個人施展伎倆：對國家、對人類，
on all organisations.
對所有組織。
He’s playing tricks all the time to make you learn so many things, but you don’t
祂不斷施展伎倆好讓你學到這麼多東西，但你卻不自知
want to learn.
不想學習。
That’s the only politics.
這就是唯一的政治。
These politics are nothing but children’s play, they are of no use.
人類的政治不過是兒戲，毫無用處。
This is just you want to play with cards and you sit down and play; that’s all, to me.
這就像你想玩牌，坐下來玩就是了；對我來說，僅此而已。
Otherwise there’s no politics for me.
否則對我來說就沒有政治可言
What is economics of God?
什麼是神的經濟學？
That’s the only economics that reins.
那才是唯一主宰的經濟學
No other economics reins for me.
對我而言，沒有其他經濟學能主宰一切
His economics is that matter doesn’t give you joy.
祂的經濟學是物質無法帶給你快樂。
He gives you something that gives you joy, that gives you compassion, love, security,
祂給予你帶來歡樂、帶來慈悲、愛與安全感的東西，
health, innocence.
健康、純真。
Above all it gives you the power to love others: tremendous power it is.
最重要的是，祂賜予你愛他人的力量：那是無比巨大的力量。
We have never used the power of love, never.
我們從未使用過愛的力量，從未。
Always we have used the power of hatred.
我們總是利用仇恨的力量。
All our politics and economics is based on hatred.
我們所有的政治與經濟基礎都建立在仇恨之上。
We create goods to sell by seeing what weaknesses people have: like England or America and all
我們利用人們的弱點來製造商品出售：例如英國或美國等等
these Western countries.
這些西方國家。
In India the crooks found out that there are many seekers in these countries — all right,
在印度，那些騙子發現這些國家有許多求道者——好吧，
export all the crooks!
把所有的騙子都出口出去！
They all came out of the jail and are here back.
他們全都從監獄出來，現在又回來這裡了。
They have got Rolls Royces, they have got big, big huge houses, they have got huge big
他們擁有勞斯萊斯，有超級豪宅，有巨大的私人飛機，這些你都看不到。
aeroplanes and you can’t see that.
飛機有多大你根本無法想像。
This is the economics of human beings.
這就是人類的經濟法則。
But God’s economics is such that if you have any want, it looks after you.
但神的經濟法則卻是：只要你有所需，祂必看顧你。
But it gives you a desire for the right type of wants.
但祂讓你對那些真正值得追求的事物產生渴望。
Because the whole system changes, the whole value system changes.
因為整個系統改變了，整個價值觀體系也隨之轉變。
A person who is a realised-soul would like to have vibrations flowing all the time.
一個覺醒的靈魂會希望讓生命能量持續流動。
Today I had taken my grandchildren to a shop to buy them a sweater.
今天我帶孫子們去商店買毛衣。
It’s very difficult because they are realised-souls, all of them.
這真的很難，因為他們都是自覺靈，每一個都是。
So I gave them a very beautiful one.
所以我給了他們一個非常美麗的。
I said, “How do you like it?”
我問：「你們覺得如何？」
They said, “No, it’s very uncomfortable."
他們回答：「不，這很不舒服。」
It was acrylic.
那是壓克力的。
They just can’t have it.
他們就是不能接受。
I said, “But it’s quite nice and cheap."
我說：「但那很不錯又便宜。」
So she refused to have it.
所以她拒絕要這個。
Then it was semi-acrylic: refused to have it.
然後我又選了一件半壓克力材的材質：她還是不肯。
Then I gave her wool.
最後我選了一件純羊毛的給她。
I said, “But this wool will be only one when you can have ten like these if you buy
我說：「可是這件純羊毛的只能買一件，如果買壓克力的，你可以買十件。」
acrylic."
壓克力。
She said, “Better to have one which you can wear, than to have ten which you cannot
她說：「寧可擁有一件你能穿的，勝過十件你穿不了的。」
wear."
「穿不了的。」
The whole value system changes, to have too many things becomes useless!
整個價值觀都改變了，擁有太多東西反而沒用！
Have one which is comfortable to your being.
擁有一樣讓你感到舒適的東西就好。
Somehow they have reached even rationally, through your science and to such points, that
不知怎麼的，他們甚至透過科學理性達到這個認知，
Sahaja Yoga just fits into it.
霎哈嘉瑜伽恰好融入其中。
I sometimes feel all these things have created the beautiful ring for the diamond of Sahaja
有時我覺得這一切彷彿打造了一個精美的戒指，
Yoga to just fit into it.
只為讓霎哈嘉瑜伽這顆鑽石完美鑲嵌其中。
For example people are now realising that there is no sense in creating plastic.
舉例來說，人們現在已經意識到生產塑膠製品毫無意義。
But say about thirty years back, people would have been proud to have a sofa set made out
但大約三十年前，人們會以擁有一套塑膠沙發組為榮。
of plastic.
用塑膠製成的。
We had a ship from Norway, I remember, about thirty years back, and they were going round
我記得大約三十年前，我們有一艘來自挪威的船，他們四處展示
to show us how they had made plastic railings for the staircases: beautiful plastic railings.
向我們展示他們如何製作樓梯的塑料扶手：精美的塑料扶手。
And we were all very much enamoured in India, how they had made it.
我們在印度都對此深深著迷，驚嘆他們是如何做到的。
While we can make very beautiful carvings, but we thought this was wonderful: looks so
雖然我們能雕刻出非常精美的作品，但我們覺得這實在太棒了：看起來如此
nice, washable, you can wash it, no polishing needed, no painting needed, wonderful thing
美觀、可清洗，你可以直接水洗，不需要打磨，也不需要上漆，真是了不起的東西
you know, just go ahead with it.
就這麼簡單方便。
But now the same Norwegians are asking Indians to create some things for them out of wood.
但現在同樣的挪威人卻要求印度人用木材為他們製作一些東西。
So the whole value system changes, as soon as you start feeling your Self, your being.
所以整個價值體系都會改變，就在你開始感受真我、感受你的存有那一刻。
Because your being is absolute: it is truth, and its complete beauty manifests when you
因為你的存在是絕對的：它就是真理，而當你...時，它的完美之美就會顯現。
start, with your willpower, accepting the new challenge that is given to you.
開始，用你的意志力，接受眼前的新挑戰。
And that is the time where this built-in ego of ages stands out: “Why?
這時那積年累月的內在自我便會浮現：「為什麼？」
Why to do like this?”
「為什麼要這麼做？」
So many things in the society that we have, whether in India or here or anywhere in the
無論在印度或這裡或世界任何地方，我們的社會中存在著太多
whole world, are so shocking that only after Realisation you realise that you have been
全世界的一切，是如此令人震驚，直到你獲得自覺後才意識到，
going on with it all these lives and your parents have been and their parents have been.
這些生生世世以來你一直都這樣持續著，你的父母、乃至祖輩也都是如此。
It’s absolutely a shocking thing.
這完全是件令人震撼的事。
But for that you have to first get your Realisation.
但首先你必須獲得自覺。
That part is not so difficult, as I told you, because the time has come for many to get
這部分正如如我所說並不難，因為對許多人來說，時機已經成熟
Realisation.
自覺的時刻到了。
But how many will enjoy it you cannot say, because Mr Ego is the worst enemy of human
但有多少人能真正享受自覺的喜悅，這很難說，因為自我是人類最大的敵人
beings.
這一點千真萬確。
First of all they cannot take it from anyone else but themselves.
首先，他們除了自己以外，無法接受任何人。
This is the big problem.
這就是最大的問題。
“All right,” I say, “even take that way!”
「好吧，」我說，「就算那樣也行！」
But it cannot be done.
但這是不可能的。
Now supposing somebody has to do it: it’s not a very easy thing you know, it’s a very
假設非得有人來做這件事：這可不是件簡單的事情，你知道的，這非常
difficult thing to do such a thing, and it’s horribly embarrassing.
困難，而且超級尷尬。
You have to do something which people think they can do themselves!You can imagine how
你得去做別人自以為能做好的事！你可以想像那有多
embarrassing it is.
麼難堪。
Only a Mother can take such a situation that she knows her children are like that, doesn’t
只有一個母親才能接受這種情況，明知孩子就是這般模樣
matter.
此事。
But any other person would say, “Go to hell what do I care!
但其他任何人都會說：「去你的，關我什麼事！」
Why should I take the responsibility of anybody and why should I say all these things to them?
我為什麼要承擔別人的責任？又為什麼要對他們說這些話？
If they are so egoistical, let them go to hell!”
要是他們那麼自私，就讓他們下地獄吧！
This is what is really the situation.
這就是真實的情況。
But supposing somebody is nothing but compassion and love: supposing.
但假設某個人充滿慈悲與愛：假設如此。
I mean, it’s a supposition for many people: they can’t believe it.
我的意思是，對許多人來說這是個假設：他們無法相信。
Supposing someone is, then someone has to do it.
假設某人真是如此，那麼就必須這個人去做
And if someone has to do it why be so angry about it?
而如果有人必須去做，又何必對此事如此生氣？
This I have failed to understand.
這一點我一直無法理解。
Like in Spain one gentleman got Realisation and he couldn’t believe that it has happened.
就像在西班牙，有位紳士得到了真覺，他簡直不敢相信這件事真的發生了。
And he came to me and argued with me in a very funny manner.
然後他用一種非常滑稽的方式來找我爭論。
He said, “But why is it you had to do it?”
他說：「但為什麼非得是你去做呢？」
I said, “You do it!”
我說：「你自己來啊！」
(laughter) That he can’t do!
（笑聲）這他可辦不到！
I said, “All right, now if you are angry for that…”
我說：「好吧，現在如果你為了這個生氣…」
Because it has happened in my presence, he was angry with me.
因為這事就發生在我面前，所以他對我很生氣。
He was thinking why shouldn’t he do it.
他當時在想為什麼他不能自己做呢？
I said, “All right now you can do it but before this you could not!”
我說：「好了，現在你可以做了，但之前你就是不行！」
So he was very angry for that also.
所以他對此也感到非常生氣。
He said, “Why should God make one person do it?”
他說：「為什麼上帝要讓一個人來做這件事？」
I said, “It’s really horrible I tell you!
我說：「我告訴你，這真的很糟糕！
If He had given one hundred people to do it, it would be much better.
如果祂讓一百個人來做這件事，情況會好很多。」
I would have taken some rest myself.
我自己本該休息一下的。
Because I am already sixty years of age and when am I going to retire?
畢竟我已經六十歲了，什麼時候才能退休呢？
But it’s not so.
但事實並非如此。
What can I do?”
我能怎麼辦呢？」
Then he was still angry with me.
當時他還在生我的氣。
He said, “But must be something why you are doing it."
他說：「但你一定有原因才會這麼做。」
I said, “Yes there is!”
我回答：「確實有！」
“What is it?”
「是什麼原因？」
I said, “Love."
我說：「愛。」
He couldn’t understand that, he couldn’t understand that.
他無法理解，他無法明白。
So he went on with very great anger still.
因此他依舊帶著極大的憤怒繼續前行。
He said, “But must be something!”
他說：「肯定有原因！」
Then foolishly one of the Sahaja Yogis, brought my shoes down to put in my feet, which I never
當時有位霎哈嘉瑜伽修行者將我的鞋子拿來要幫我穿上，這是我從未
asked them, I never asked them, I have never ask them, I would not like it.
要求過的，我從未要求過，我從未要他們這麼做，我也不喜歡這樣。
But they like it because there are vibrations in my shoes!
但他們喜歡這樣做，因為我的鞋子裡有生命能量！
Out of their self-interest that they’re doing it.
他們是出於自己的慾望才這麼做的。
And he said, “This is the reason why you are doing all this!”
他說：「這就是你之所以做這一切的原因！」
I said, “Really?
我說：「真的嗎？
It’s very wise."
這非常明智。」
And at that point he left Sahaja Yoga.
就在那一刻，他離開了霎哈嘉瑜伽。
So there are such wise people in this world.
這世上確實有很多自作聰明的人。
I am talking of something very great and the wisdom of people is so limited.
我所談論之事何其偉大，而人們的智慧卻如此有限。
The quality of wisdom is poor.
這般智慧的品質委實低劣。
They are intelligent, well-educated but quality of wisdom is very poor.
他們雖機敏博學，但智慧的品質卻十分低下。
But in a village [if] you go, you always find villagers more wise than the city people,
但在鄉村裡，你會發現村民往往比城市人更有智慧，
I tell you.
我告訴你，
The reason is they live with the Mother Earth, they take all their innocence.
原因是他們與大地之母生活在一起，保有純真本性，
Without innocence you cannot have wisdom.
沒有純真就無法擁有智慧。
Innocence is the basis of wisdom.
純真是智慧的基礎。
Normally people who are living in the city have to deal with such crooks that part of
通常生活在都市中的人不得不與那些騙子周旋
the wisdom is lost.
以至於大部分的智慧流失了。
And that’s why the quality of wisdom I find is lacking.
這就是為什麼我發現智慧的品質有所欠缺。
If that is there, Sahaja Yoga works out, it gives you what is your own and you enjoy what
如果有智慧，霎哈嘉瑜伽就會發揮作用，它會給予你屬於你自己的東西，而你享受著
is your own.
專屬你的一切。
Now take a simple question, a simple thing.
現在舉個簡單的例子：
You have got say for example your property, say your ornaments, kept with someone; and
比如說，你把你的財產，比如你的首飾，託付給某人保管；
somebody knows the keys and the ornaments.
而這個人知道鑰匙和首飾的所在。
Say your forefathers have given the key to a person and the person comes and says that,
假設你的祖先把鑰匙交給某人，這個人過來跟你說：
“I have got the keys with me, you take it and use your own money."
「鑰匙在我這，你拿去用你自己的錢吧。」
Will you get angry with that person for that?
你會因此對那個人發脾氣嗎？
For nothing at all, for giving nothing, will you get angry?
就因為他什麼都沒給，什麼都沒付出，你還會生氣嗎？
But immediately they become like a bull: “No we’ll not have it!”
但他們馬上就像一頭公牛一樣說：「不，我們不要！」
“But why?
「但為什麼？
Please have!”
請收下！」
I persuade.
我建議。
“Please have it!
「請您收下吧！
Enjoy it.
好好享受。
It is your own.
這是屬於你的。
You have been desiring it, you have been wanting it, please have it."
你一直以來地追尋，一直想要，請收下吧。
They say, “Why should we have it?
他們說：「我們為何該收下這個？」
Who are you to give us the key?”
「你憑什麼給我們鑰匙？」
I mean, “But I have it!
我的意思是：「可是鑰匙在我這兒啊！」
What am I to do?”
我能怎麼辦？」
I am imploring, “Please just have it."
我懇求著：「拜託你就收下吧。」
But they are adamant just like bulls you know.
但他們倔強得跟牛一樣，你知道的。
Bulls are easy, easier people.
牛還比較容易應付，比人好搞多了。
I tell you, bulls are much easier.
我跟你說，公牛容易對付多了。
If there is a bull like that in India what we do, we take some red chillies and put to
在印度要是碰到那種公牛，我們就拿些辣椒粉抹在
the nose and it will get up.
牠鼻子上，牠就會立刻站起來了。
But what should we do with human beings?
但我們該怎麼對付人類呢？
They are stuck-up people and this really amazes me.
他們就是一群自以為是的人，這真的讓我感到驚訝。
Aren’t you seeking, aren’t you seeking?
你不是在尋找嗎，你不是在尋找嗎？
What more do you want me to say?
你還想讓我說什麼？
It is impossible.
這真是不可能。
I mean I discussed with them I said, “What should we do with these people?”
我的意思是，我和他們討論過，我問：「我們該怎麼對待這些人？」
They come, get Realisation, disappear just like that!
他們來了，得到自覺，然後就這樣消失了！
After ten months they’ll appear, “Mother I developed this trouble, that trouble."
十個月後他們又出現了，「母親，我出了這個問題、那個問題。」
But why not?
但為什麼不呢？
It’s all free to you.
這對你來說都是免費的。
We had in India a great advantage I should say because we know what to expect, first
我應該說，我們在印度有個很大的優勢，因為我們知道會發生什麼事，首先
of all.
就是。
Everyone knows: whether you go to a villager or to an educated man, everyone knows what
大家都知道：不論你是去找村民還是有受過教育的人，每個人都知道會發生什麼事
to expect, everyone.
每個人都知道。
Secondly they know how to make out a real person.
其次他們知道如何辨識真實的人。
I mean not the westernised [ones].
我指的是沒有西化的[印度人]。
The westernised I don’t know but otherwise.
西化的我不清楚，但其他的倒是知道。
Then also we have a great advantage of certain prophesies made in our country so people know
我們國家流傳的某些預言帶來極大優勢，讓民眾能知曉
when it is going to happen, how to pin down the thing.
事件將於何時發生，如何準確掌握關鍵。
Now you too had prophesies made, like a person like William Blake.
你們那邊也曾有人做出預言，比如威廉·布雷克這樣的人物。
But who understands William Blake here?
但這裡有誰真正理解威廉·布雷克呢？
No one!
沒人！
Because he is on a different plane and when he speaks no one understands him.
因為他來自不同的次元，當他說話時沒人能理解他。
So it has all been prophesised that you are going to get it, this is going to happen.
所以這一切早已預言你將會得到它，這件事必定會發生。
There’s a book written thousands of years back that this is going to happen in 1970,
有本數千年前寫下的書預言這件事將在 1970 年實現，
that people are going to get transformation, that they are going to get into a system,
人們將會得到轉化，他們將進入一個體系，
a new system will be developed by which they will get their Realisation.
一個新的體系將會被建立，透過這個體系他們將獲得自覺。
There will not be any need to go to hospitals any more after that.
之後他們將不再需要去醫院。
Even the word is there that they will not go to any rugunalay (रुग्णालय)
甚至有這樣的說法：他們將不再去任何रुग्णालय（醫院）。
means a hospital.
意指醫院。
So clearly it is given thousands of years back!
所以很明顯，這預言早在幾千年前就已經發出！
And people are looking forward for that.
而人們正期待著那一天的到來。
But the tragedy is: most of the seekers are born in the West.
但可悲的是：大多數求道者都出生在西方。
It’s like one has the teeth so he cannot get food and the one who has got food, has
就像一個人有牙齒卻吃不到食物，而能吃食物的人卻
no teeth!
沒有牙齒！
And that is why Sahaja Yoga takes time to develop.
這就是為什麼霎哈嘉瑜伽需要時間來發展。
It will always because it’s such a process, living process.
這永遠會是這樣的過程，一個活生生的過程。
And this is the living process of the living God which you must ask for.
而這就是活神的生命歷程，你必須尋求。
You must not any more look at things which are done artificially: like a baptism, like
你不應該再關注那些人為的儀式：比如洗禮，就像
in Indian communities we’ll have a ceremony actually called as a your ‘gopavita’,
在印度社群中，我們有個儀式實際上稱為你的「聖線禮」，
where they say that, “Now you are a twice born!”
他們會說：「現在你是重生之人！」
At the age of eight years it is done actually.
在八歲時確實會完成這個儀式。
Even Muslims do that.
連回教徒也會這樣做。
And everybody gets a kind of a thread in India to celebrate that: “Now you have become
在印度，每個人都會得到一種線來慶祝這件事：「現在你已經成為
a Brahmin, you know the Brahma, you are a realised-soul."
一位婆羅門，你認識梵天，你是一位已覺醒的靈魂。」
I mean certified!
我的意思是，他們被認證了！
They move about like that!
他們到處炫耀！
They think that they are realised-souls.
他們自以為是開悟的靈魂。
And in America there are many who certify themselves as twice born.
而在美國，有很多人自稱是重生者。
[They] certify: self-certificate.
[他們]進行認證：自行認證。
I am surprised.
我很驚訝。
In this country, I am told that people give self-certificate that they are totally mad!
在這個國家，我聽說人們會給自己開證明 說自己完全瘋了！
(laughter) I didn’t know.
(笑聲) 我以前不知道。
But really I met some people who came to my programme and I said, “Why are you shaking
但實際上我遇到了一些來參加我節目的人，我問：「你們為什麼抖得
so much?”
這麼厲害？」
He said, “We are certified mad people."
他們說：「我們是有認證的瘋子。」
I said, “What?”
我說：「什麼？」
“Yes, we are coming from lunatic asylum."
「對，我們是從精神病院來的。」
But this type of self-certificate that people have, they go about.
但人們就是有這種自我認證的方式到處招搖。
And how to tell them?
我該怎麼跟他們解釋呢？
It’s impossible, you know.
你知道，這根本不可能。
I can understand a drunkard but I can’t understand a person in all sanity becoming
我能理解一個醉漢，但我無法理解一個完全清醒的人竟會如此
so drunk with stupidity.
變得如此愚蠢。
It’s impossible to understand.
這實在難以理解。
And this is one of the drawbacks, I feel, in me, that I don’t know how to convince
而這正是我感受到的自身缺點之一——我不知道該如何說服他人。
people that, “Please have it now, this is yours, go ahead with it.
快趁現在享用吧，這是你的了，儘管拿去。
You are hungry.
你餓了。
This is food for you.
這是為你準備的精神食物。
Better have it!”
趁熱吃最好！
And then after Realisation as I said that, you are the one who can do it.
接著，就像我所說的，自覺後，一切就都由你自己掌控了。
All the progress later on is completely done by you.
之後的所有進展都是完全由你自己完成的。
The complete vidya, the complete technique, the Divine technique, how to operate the Divine
完整的知識，完整的技巧，神聖的技巧，如何運用這神聖的
technique is all told to you and you have to just see and work it out.
技巧全都告訴你了，你只需要觀察並實踐出來。
If you want, you can work it out, anyone.
如果你想，你可以做到，任何人都行。
I have seen people who came to me absolutely possessed, absolutely possessed: today they
我曾見過有人來找我時完全被附身，完全被掌控：如今他們
are great Sahaja Yogis.
都成了優秀的霎哈嘉瑜伽士。
People came mentally absolutely we can call them half mad or some of them full mad, certified
這些人來時心智狀態完全——我們可以說半瘋，有些人根本是全瘋，還有醫生證明
mad and they are today great Sahaja Yogis giving Realisation to people.
當年他們瘋狂放縱，如今卻成為偉大的霎哈嘉行者，為人們帶自覺。
Yes, yes!
是的，正是如此！
People who were drunkards, alcoholics, drug addicts: all sorts of people came.
那些曾經的酒鬼、酗酒者和吸毒者：各式各樣的人都來了。
They all have got Realisation and they are settled down as very good Sahaja Yogis.
他們全都獲得自覺，並安定下來成為優秀的霎哈嘉瑜珈士。
But how can you treat a person who is stupid?
但你要怎麼對待一個愚蠢的人呢？
(laughter) Ego makes you stupid, I tell you.
（笑聲）我告訴你，自我會讓你變笨。
Ego, the result of ego, is stupidity!
自我，自我導致的結果，就是愚蠢！
People do so many stupid things these days that even little children laugh like this,
現在人們做這麼多愚蠢的事情，連小孩看到別人做這些事都會哈哈大笑。
when they see people doing it.
當他們看到別人這麼做時。
But to them it is nothing.
但對他們來說這不算什麼。
They think, “Oh we are very great!”
他們心想：「喔我們可真是了不起！」
This ego business is really very blinding.
這種自我真是讓人盲目。
But one doesn’t have to worry about it because Christ Himself has made arrangements that
但我們無需擔憂，因為基督已親自安排了這一切
He sucks in your ego.
祂會消融你的自我
He does that.
祂就是如此
Surprisingly the One who came just to do that.
令人驚奇的是，祂來到世上是為了做這件事
I don’t know what a mess they have created out of Him, that those who follow have much
我不知道他們把祂扭曲成什麼樣子，以至於跟隨祂的人反而
more of it.
更加自大。
I mean, you see anybody in charge of the church he won’t talk to you; he’s a snooty fellow!
我是說，你看看教堂裡那些管事的，誰會跟你說話？他們全都傲慢得要命！
You don’t know which way to approach.
你不知道該該如何接近他們。
He walks with five revolvers around him.
他們身邊總像是帶著五把左輪手槍。
If you say anything, he may hit you or do whatever, and you don’t know.
你要是敢吭聲，他可能會揍你或做出什麼事來，誰也說不準。
It’s easier to face a madman than to face a priest sometimes – it’s difficult.
有時候面對瘋子還比面對神父來得更容易——真是難搞。
God knows how he will attack you.
天曉得他會怎麼對付你]。
Today I had a little encounter and I was rather worried.
今天我遇到了一件小事，讓我相當擔憂。
But this is what it is: that Christ, a person so Divine.
但事實就是如此：那基督，一位如此神聖的存在。
I mean there’s nothing left in Him as a person (in Christianity).
我的意思是，在祂身上（在基督教中）他沒有人性的因子。
It’s nothing [of] Divinity.
他完全是神性。
He came on this earth and nicely people have cooked him, I really tell you.
他來到世上，卻被人糟蹋了，我實在地告訴你。
I mean I don’t know how they could make anything out of Him this kind of nonsense.
我是說，我實在不懂怎麼有人能從祂身上編出這種荒謬的東西。
That this ‘Saint’ Paul of all the persons was included in the Bible I was amazed!
在所有人物中，這位所謂的「聖徒」保羅竟被列入聖經，令我驚愕不已！
When I saw the Bible I said, “From where does he come?”
當我翻閱聖經時不禁問道：「這個人究竟是從哪裡冒出來的？」
And now they have started this charismatic movement; and go and have a look at them:
如今他們發起靈恩運動，去瞧瞧他們吧：
they are epileptic.
都患了癲癇。
And horrible things they are doing in the name of Christ.
他們竟以基督之名行可怖之事。
Can you imagine?
你能想像嗎？
He drove out the spirits from people and here the people are calling spirits!
基督把邪靈從人身上趕走，現在這些人卻在呼喚邪靈！
It’s such a mess I tell you!
我告訴你，這簡直是一團亂！
You all have to help me because you are all wise people and sensible ones.
你們都必須幫助我，因為你們都是明智且明事理的人。
And we have to see now how many remain in Sahaja Yoga; that’s the sign of wisdom according
現在我們得看看有多少人留在霎哈嘉瑜伽裡；這就是智慧的標誌。
to me.
對我來說。
Maybe your style may be different, I don’t know.
或許你的風格會不一樣，我也不知道。
But my style, I understand that, if you have pure intelligence, pure intelligence which
但我的風格是，我理解如果你擁有純粹的智慧，這種許多人具備的純粹智慧，
many have, you suddenly know what it is.
你突然就會明白那是什麼。
As I have seen in Spain one fellow, he was a lawyer.
我在西班牙遇見一位律師。
He listened to one of my lectures and sparkled him: just sparkled with it.
他聽了我的一場演講後整個人都被點亮了：就是那種豁然開朗的感覺。
I don’t know what made him think that way.
我不知道是什麼觸動了他的想法。
I don’t know at which point he got up.
我也不確定他是從哪個段落開始被觸動的。
But he said, “That’s the truth.
但他說：「那就是真理。」
I can see clearly this is the truth."
我可以清楚地看到這就是真理。」
There are many like that.
像這樣的人很多。
They may not even get Realisation but rationally they just reach the point, “Yes this is
他們甚至可能還沒獲得自覺，但理性上已到達「是的，這就是」的境界。
the truth.
真理
Cannot be anything else but the truth."
只能是真理，不可能是別的。」
You need not be very well educated for that or need not go to any one of these universities.
要理解這點，你不需要受過高等教育，也不必上任何一所名牌大學。
You could be a very simple housewife to understand.
即使是一名平凡的家庭主婦也能明白。
But a person who has common sense which is based on wisdom, should know that you have
但一個擁有基於智慧的常識的人，應該明白你必須
to become your Spirit.
成為靈。
All other nonsensical ideas like painting your hair, you are not going to go to God,
其他那些荒謬的想法，像是染頭髮之類的，你不會因此就接近上帝，
take it from me.
相信我說的。
By painting your hair, if you can go to God then it is the easiest!
只要染髮就能接近神？那是最容易的啦！
Or by putting nails into your noses or by standing on your head, or by jumping morning
或是在鼻孔裡釘釘子、倒立、從早跳到晚，
till evening, or calling God, morning till evening: how can you go to God?
從早到晚呼喚神名——這樣就能接近神嗎？
Something has to happen within.
真正的改變必須發自內心。
It’s evolutionary.
這是進化的過程。
It has to be something living.
必須是有生命的東西。
It’s a living God we are talking about.
我們談論的是一位活生生的神。
Whatever we do before Realisation is all dead, and dead way is not going to take you to God.
在自覺前所做的一切都是無生命的，無生命的方式無法帶你接近神。
Only after Realisation because you become the master of life, life starts flowing through
唯有在獲得「自覺」後，你才能成為生命的主人，生命才開始流淌經過
you, you can give Realisation to others.
你，你才能將「自覺」給予他人。
For the first time you start doing really something that is living.
這是首次你真正開始從事具有生命力的作為。
You can give vibrations to the flowers, you can give vibrations to the trees, you can
你能將生命能量傳遞給花朵，你能將生命能量傳遞給樹木，你能
give vibrations to the nature, whatever you touch you vibrate.
將生命能量傳遞給自然，你所觸及的一切都有生命能量。
But first you must become a realised-soul.
但首先你必須成為自覺靈。
And then you respect that Realisation.
然後你要尊重那份覺醒。
It’s a tremendous thing but it happens very quickly, very easily and that’s how you
這是一件極其非凡的事情，但它發生得非常迅速、非常容易，正因如此，
get lost.
人們很容易迷失方向。
If somebody is made to work for something with a very great difficulty, then perhaps
如果有人必須付出極大的努力才能獲得某樣東西，那麼或許
people realise that, “Oh we must have it!”
人們會意識到：「哦，我們必須擁有它！」
But if the forefathers have earned quite a lot, they want to distribute to their children
但如果祖先已經積累了相當多的財富，他們希望將所有財富都
freely, everything.
他們希望將所有財富都慷慨地分配給子孫後代。
Why to worry?
這有什麼好擔心的呢？
But we must have wisdom to use that with respect.
但我們必須以尊重的智慧善用之。
It has been earned with very great difficulties.
畢竟，這一切得來不易，艱辛萬分。
For example the crucifixion of Christ: without His crucifixion we could not have had Sahaja
以基督的受難為例：若無祂的犧牲，我們今日便不可能有霎哈嘉
Yoga today, could not have.
瑜伽，根本不可能。
Unless and until He’s awakened within us, we cannot give Realisation to people whether
除非且直到祂在我們內在覺醒，否則無論你接受與否，
you like it or not.
我們都無法為人們帶來真我覺醒。
So these people have dedicated themselves completely, they have built everything within
這些前人將自己完全奉獻，在你內在建構了一切
you and that’s how you get it so easily but you must have respect, you must have understanding,
你才能如此輕易地獲得自覺，但必須懷抱尊重，必須保持理解，
otherwise all their efforts are lost and also your seeking is lost.
否則他們所有的努力都將白費，而你的追尋也將徒勞無功。
May God bless you.
求道者：（聲音模糊不清），
I can allow you to ask me a few questions but these Caxton Hall people are rather angry
錫呂‧瑪塔吉：不行。
because we have been always going very late.
我很抱歉。
So I promised that I’ll leave this hall by nine fifteen.
真的，一開始你就是不行，就是辦不到。
Gavin says I use 150 year old English sometimes.
就是這樣設定的。
Yes please?
整個情況就是這樣。
Shri Mataji: What’s this?
現在我必須坦白告訴你一件事。
Seeker: inaudible.
好嗎？
Shri Mataji: Why do you want to do without the picture?
這件事我從未告訴過任何人，但今天我必須向你坦白。
Really, you can’t do it in the beginning, just can’t do it.
就像我告訴過你的，你的先人已經解決了這個問題，對吧？
I have not told this to anyone but today I must confess to you something.
至今你從未認出他們，以前也從未認出過。
You always refused them.
你總是拒絕他們。
Leave alone photograph, even bodily you never recognised.
別說照片了，就連親眼見面你也從未認出過。
You crucified them, you gave them poisons, you beat them, did everything.
你們把祂們釘在十字架上，給他們毒藥，毆打他們，無所不用其極。
But in this working you have to recognise me.
但在這一切過程中，你們必須認出我。
I am sorry.
我很抱歉。
This is the first time I am saying this.
這是我第一次說這件事。
Because it was not wise to say but now it’s [the] ninth year I am running in this England.
因為之前說這種話並不理智，但現在已是我在英國奔波了九年。
I kept my mouth shut!
我一直保持沉默！
Of course you can’t crucify me, I think, but that’s a fact.
當然，我想你們不能把我釘在十字架上，我想是這麼想的，但事實就是這樣。
You have to recognise me, otherwise things are not going to work out.
你得認出我，否則事情就不會順利。
People want to get their cancers cured free, they want to get their Realisation free, everything
人們想免費治癒癌症，想免費獲得自覺，什麼都想要
done free by me.
由我免費完成。
But my photograph or anything to do with me they don’t want to do it.
但他們不願意接受我的照片，或任何與我有關的東西。
So it’s not possible.
所以這行不通。
You have to recognise.
你必須明白這一點。
And Christ has said already about you, very clearly.
基督已經非常清楚地對你們說了關於你的事。
Because I am something special, I must say.
因為我得說，我確實與眾不同。
I am really a special person.
我真的是個特別的人。
But I don’t want to say that because it’s rather embarrassing.
但我不太想這樣說，因為這實在有點難為情。
But it is so.
但事實就是如此。
Without that do you think I can give mass Realisation to people?
若非如此，你認為我能為人們帶來大規模的自覺嗎？
There must be something about me or not, if I am doing it?That’s it.
既然我做到了，那必然是我身上有什麼特別之處，不是嗎？就是這樣。
So it is better that you recognise me; it’s better for you.
所以你們最好承認我，這對你們比較好。
I am not going to take away anything from you, nothing whatsoever.
我不會從你身上奪走任何東西，一點也不會。
What are you going to give me?
你要給我什麼呢？
Just think of it.
想想看吧
I am here to give you something but you must recognise that I am a giver, just recognise.
我來到這裡是為了給予你某些東西，但你必須認清我是一位給予者，只要認清這一點就好。
I am sorry to say but it is so.
我很抱歉這麼說，但事實就是如此。
You will gradually recognise when you’ll have vibrations.
你會逐漸知道什麼時候會有生命能量。
When I say that the vibrations, see how much it flows.
當我說這些生命能量時，看看它是多麼流暢地運作。
When I boast the vibrations flow more!
當我談到自己時，生命能量會更加強烈！
What can I too do?
我能怎麼辦？
But I am very cautious.
但我非常謹慎。
Christ said, “I am the light.
基督說：「我就是光。
I am the path."
我就是道路。」
They killed Him.
他們殺害了他。
What did He say?
祂說了什麼？
What did He say so much?
祂說了多少話？
What did He say that people killed Him and crucified Him?
祂究竟說了什麼，導致人們殺害祂並將祂釘在十字架上？
And even till today these Jews are not willing to accept Christ!
直至今日，這些猶太人仍不願意接受基督！
They want to have sufferings, so have it.
他們想要受苦，那就如他們所願。
You will have, not Christ but you will have Hitler.
你們得到的不是基督，而是希特勒。
You have to recognise.
你必須明白。
This is a compulsion on you.
這是對你的一種強制力。
I am sorry, that’s what it is.
我很抱歉，但事情就是如此。
You have to recognise the Divine.
你必須認出神性的存在。
You have to recognise.
你必須認清這一點。
It’s not easy to give Realisation to anyone.
要讓任何人自覺並不容易。
If you had seen in Spain I cured a lady whose brain was damaged, and they had removed a
如果你在西班牙看過我治癒一位腦部受損的女士，他們當時已經切除了
part of the brain, and in ten minutes that lady was cured and she started understanding
她的一部分腦組織，但在十分鐘內那位女士就被治癒了，她開始理解
everything and she started moving her hand and everything.
一切事物，並且能夠活動她的手和所有功能。
But for people you know they don’t understand, how it happened.
但你知道，有些人不明白，，事情是怎麼發生的。
It’s easy for people to understand who know what to expect.
對於那些知道會發生什麼的人來說，這很容易理解。
All the kinds of people have photographs, all these gurus have.
各種各樣的人都有照片，那些大師都有。
What have they done for you?
他們為你做了什麼？
What have they done?
他們做了些什麼？
They have just taken your money.
他們只是拿走了你的錢。
This photograph has vibrations.
這張照片有生命能量。
The first time a photograph has been taken actually authentically, thanks to your science.
這是有史以來第一次真實拍攝的照片，多虧了你們的科學技術。
You don’t have any authentic photograph of Christ.
你沒有任何一張耶穌的真實照片。
I haven’t seen any good picture except for I would say a few like Michelangelo or someone
我得說除了像米開朗基羅等極少數人畫的幾幅作品外，我還沒見過什麼好畫像
like that, very few: Rubens, Michelangelo.
諸如此類的，非常稀少：魯本斯、米開朗基羅。
Otherwise the way they make Him He was never like that!
否則他們塑造的祂，從來就不是那副模樣！
Never, never like that.
絕不，絕不會那樣。
No vibrations from them.
那些照片沒有生命能量。
So I have to tell you there is something about me.
所以，我必須告訴你關於我的一些事。
I am sorry but it is so.
很抱歉，但事實就是如此。
It’s rather dangerous to say in this great country of yours, where people don’t take
在你們這個偉大的國家裡說這些話是相當危險的，因為這裡的人們不太
things easily, but you better take it now.
輕易接受，但你最好現在就接受。
It’s late.
時間緊迫。
Already eight years I have worked in this great country of yours because this is an
我在你們這個偉大的國家已經工作了八年，因為這是一個
important country.
重要的國家。
You do not know the value of this country; you do not know what role it is going to play
你不了解這個國家的價值；你不明白它將扮演
for the whole humanity of the world.
對全世界人類而言的
That’s why I have come here.
關鍵角色。這就是我來到這裡的原因。
I have not come as an immigrant at all.
我完全不是以移民身份來的。
My husband got a posting here.
我丈夫被派駐到這裡工作。
He was elected by a hundred and thirty-five nations and that’s why I am here.
他被 135 個國家選中，所以我才會在這裡。
It’s all organised!
這一切都是安排好！
And that’s how I am at your service here but you have to recognise my services.
這就是我在這裡為您服務的方式，但您必須認可我。
I have no union for that but you have to understand this.
我沒有加入任何工會來做這件事，但您必須明白這一點。
If you do not recognise my services nothing is going to work out.
如果您不認可我，一切都不會順利。
I am sorry but that’s how I am made.
很抱歉，但這就是我的原則。
Jewish Seeker: (says Something about recognising Mother and Christ)
猶太求道者：（談及關於辨認母親與基督的某些觀點）
Shri Mataji: Because you are all conditioned, you are a Jew, you are conditioned.
錫呂‧瑪塔吉：因為你們都被制約了，你是猶太人，你被制約了。
So you have to get out of this condition.
所以你必須擺脫這種制約。
You see you’ll be surprised: you can make out a Jew just like that.
你看你會很驚訝：你可以就這樣辨認出猶太人。
When the Kundalini rises She stops at the point of Christ.
當昆達里尼能量升起時，祂會在基督的點位停駐。
This is the biggest problem of the Jews.
這就是猶太人面臨的最大困境。
Where are they going to go?
他們究竟該何去何從？
You have to save them.
你必須拯救他們。
Jewish Seeker: Inaudible
猶太求道者：聽不清楚
Shri Mataji: This is all your conditioning my child.
錫呂‧瑪塔吉：這全是你的制約，我的孩子。
How can we understand Him?
我們該如何理解祂？
You tell me.
你告訴我。
How can you understand Him?
你怎能理解祂？
You cannot understand Him.
你無法理解祂。
Jews didn’t want to.
猶太人並不願意去理解。
You see this is a common practice of human beings: they don’t want to recognise, that’s
你看這是人類的通病：他們不願承認，
the main thing.
最主要的事情。
Afterwards of course, even the Christians so-called who have built big, big churches,
後來當然了，就算是所謂那些建造了超大教堂的基督徒們，
never recognised Him.
也從未認出祂來。
At that time, how many were there?
當時有多少基督徒？
His disciples: useless people!
祂的門徒：一群廢物！
You ask me, I’ll tell you about them!
你問我，我就跟你說說他們！
Absolutely useless!
簡直毫無用處！
They wouldn’t believe in Him till He got His resurrection then they started saying,
直到祂復活了，他們才肯相信，然後才開始說，
“Oh God, Oh God!”
「天啊，天啊！」
Otherwise this Mathews, he was a terrible man and he wouldn’t recognise that there
除此之外，馬太福音的作者馬太是個糟糕的人，他根本不相信耶穌的存在
could be this conception.
會有這樣的觀念。
They can’t understand Divine things.
他們無法理解神聖的事物。
What have Jews achieved?
猶太人達成了什麼成就？
You tell me.
你告訴我。
You just see the way they pray: everything nonsensical just like Christians, just like
你就看看他們祈禱的方式：一切都毫無意義，就像基督徒一樣，就像
Hindus, Muslims, everybody’s just the same.
印度教徒、回教徒，每個人都一模一樣。
What are Islams doing?
回教徒在做什麼？
What a ‘sensible’ thing they are doing!
他們做的真是『明智』啊！
It’s a different world I tell you.
我告訴你，那是個不同的世界。
You will understand yourself when you will come to that level and see for yourself.
當你達到那個境界親眼目睹時，就會自行明白了。
We have many Jews now here sitting down, many Jews now; who know [that] while raising the
我們這裡現在坐著許多猶太人，非常多猶太人；他們知道當你提升
Kundalini you have to take the name of Christ and if it is in the stomach you have to take
昆達里尼時必須呼喚基督之名，而如果它在腹部則必須呼喚
the name of Moses.
摩西之名。
You don’t know where Moses is settled down and where is that David’s star is, do you
你不知道摩西的居住地在哪，也不知道大衛之星在哪裡，對吧
know that?
知道嗎？
In your being?
這一切又有什麼用呢？
So what’s the use of all this talking isn’t it, when you don’t know where Christ is,
所以這一切交談有何意義，當你不知道基督在哪、
where Moses is, where the star is?
摩西在哪、星星在哪？
You don’t know anything, anything at all and what are you fighting about?
你什麼都不懂，根本一無所知，到底在爭論什麼？
But we can show you in the Kundalini.
但我們可以透過昆達里尼能量向你展示這一切。
But be wise and humble.
但要保持智慧與謙遜。
Without humility you cannot go in Sahaja Yoga because it’s Divine.
若沒有謙卑之心，就無法進入霎哈嘉瑜伽，因為那是神聖的。
All right?
好嗎？
It’s nothing like clubbing or conditioning.
這完全不像去夜店狂歡或健身。
It is something that you really feel, “Your hands will speak!”
這是一種你真切感受到「你的雙手會說話！」的體驗。
Christ has said.
基督曾說。
You can see.
你感受的到。
Even a child can see, yourself.
連小孩都能感覺。
All right?
好嗎？
So do not live with any conditioning because you are born a Jew.
所以不要活在任何制約之中，只因為你生來就是猶太人。
Supposing you are born a Muslim, take it from me, you would have hated yourself! (laughing)
假設你出生在回教徒家庭，相信我，你早就恨透自己！(笑)
Isn’t it?
不是嗎？
It’s surprising.
這令人感到驚訝
I mean you could have been born in a Muslim before.
我是說你前世可能投胎成回教徒啊。
I have seen many like that.
我看過很多這樣的人。
With great hatred people are born in the other religion and they must have hated one thing
人們帶著極大的仇恨出生在其他宗教中，他們一定在某世怨恨某件事
in one life and in another life, they are hating another.
而在另一世，他們又怨恨另一件事。
It’s all hatred.
這全是憎恨。
This is not Judaism, this is not Moses, this is not that.
這不是猶太教，這不是摩西，這根本不是那回事。
It’s very different.
這截然不同。
Sahaja Yoga will teach you that they are all Brothers and Sisters and Father and Mother
霎哈嘉瑜伽會教你，他們都是兄弟姊妹與父母
and Son and we are just fighting against that family which is Divine.
以及子女，而我們只是在與這個神聖家庭對抗。
You see, what these religions have done is that they have put you up [into] conditionings
你看，這些宗教所做的是讓你陷入制約
and into ego trips, and these ego trips are funny you see.
以及自我之中，而這些自我其實很可笑。
Every religion has done this, that’s why this problem is there.
每個宗教都這麼做，所以才會有這個問題。
And these are not a solutions.
而這些都不是解決辦法。
If you are a true Christian, then save all of them.
如果你是個真正的基督徒，那就拯救所有人。
If you are a true Jew, save all of them.
如果你是個真正的猶太教徒，那就拯救所有人。
If you are a true Muslim, save all of them.
如果你是一名真正的回教徒，拯救他們所有人。
That’s what it is.
就是這麼一回事。
And it will happen to you.
而這將會發生在你身上。
We have an Algerian who is a Muslim, he came down here.
我們有一位阿爾及利亞人，他是回教徒，他來到了這裡。
They were all supporting fundamentalists and the young people got frightened you know.
他們都在支持那些基本教義派，把年輕人都嚇壞了，你知道嗎。
They thought they should become communists.
他們覺得自己應該要當共產主義者。
And this boy came down in London.
後來有個年輕人來到倫敦。
When he came here, I don’t know how we found him somewhere; he came down to see me and
他來這裡的時候，我也不曉得我們怎麼就找到了他；他是專程來見我的
he got his Realisation and went back and said, “No: neither this nor that.
他獲得自覺，回來後說：「都不是：既非此亦非彼。」
God is in the centre!”
「上帝位居中心！」
And he gave Realisation to so many Muslims and they come down here and they worship Christ
他讓許多回教徒領悟了真理，他們來到這裡並開始崇拜基督
they worship Mohammed, they worship all the other people, and they know what it is.
他們崇拜穆罕默德，他們崇拜其他所有神祈，他們明白了這一切的意義。
And even when I went to Paris, so many came down to see me from Algeria.
即便是當我到巴黎時，也有許多人從阿爾及利亞來見我。
We are entering into Algeria, into Lebanon, into Muslim countries.
霎哈嘉正進入阿爾及利亞、進入黎巴嫩、進入回教徒國家。
What about you people?
你們這些人呢？
How long are we going to be Christians, Jews and Hindus, this, that?
我們還要當基督徒、猶太教徒和印度教徒多久，這個、那個？
We are human beings and we are prophets now.
我們是凡人，如今我們也成為了先知。
We have to become prophets and these prophets will have powers to make others prophets as
我們必須成為先知，而這些先知將具備力量，使他人也能成為先知
prophesised by a great poet in your country, William Blake.
正如貴國偉大詩人威廉·布萊克所預言的那般。
That time has come.
那個時刻已然來臨。
You better become prophets!
你們最好都成為先知！
All right?
好嗎？
Forget it!
忘掉過去！
You’ll be all right.
你會沒事的。
Jewish Seeker: Can I come back to you on something?
猶太求道者：我可以再跟你談談一件事嗎？
My religion teaches me that we should believe in one God.
我的宗教教導我們應該相信唯一的神。
And I do, I really do.
而我也確實相信，真心誠意地相信。
Shri Mataji: But your belief is artificial.
錫呂‧瑪塔吉：但你的信仰是虛假的。
It has no meaning.
這毫無意義。
Even if you believe in ten Gods, what difference does it make?
就算你信仰十位神明，那又有什麼差別？
You see, what I am saying: “I believe!”
你看，我說的是：「我相信！」
Supposing, “I believe!”
假設，「我相信！」
Here it’s very common, “I believe!”
在這裡，「我相信！」
But Baba, you believe — so what?
但兄弟，你相信又怎樣？
Whom are you obliging?
你是在討好誰？
If you believe, what is the truth behind it?
如果你相信，背後的真理是什麼？
Show us where is God?
告訴我們，上帝在哪裡？
You believe in one God I say the…
你信奉一位上帝，我說的是…
Jewish Seeker: I believe in God and you are telling me not to.
猶太求道者：我信仰上帝，而你卻告訴我不該信。
Shri Mataji: No, No.
錫呂‧瑪塔吉：不，不是這樣的。
But I am telling you: believe in the truth.
但我要告訴你：相信真理。
All right?
好嗎？
So keep your mind open.
所以敞開你的心胸。
If you say, “I believe!” then you are closing your mind.
如果你說：「我相信！」那你就是關閉了心門。
I am saying you believe in the truth.
我是要你相信真理。
So keep yourself open.
所以保持開放的心態。
You believe into something because you are conditioned into that’s what I am saying.
你相信某件事是因為你被制約了，這就是我想說的。
If you believe into anything, you are conditioning yourself.
如果你相信任何事物，你就是在制約自己。
Whatever you have believed into is not the truth, if so show us!
你所相信的都不是真理，如果是的話就證明給我們看！
Simple thing.
簡單的道理。
Now see, you are a believer of truth, all right?
看吧，你是真相的信徒，對吧？
Believe in truth; now you find out the truth and see if it is truth or not.
相信真相；現在你去發掘真相，看它究竟是否屬實。
It’s as simple as that.
就是這麼簡單。
It’s nothing more or less.
不添油加醋。
You should be the believer of truth.
你應當成為真理的信徒。
Not because you are born as Jew, you should become a Jew and deny Christ.
但這並不意味著你生為猶太人，就應該成為猶太徒而否認基督。
Only because you are born in a Jew family, you are denying Christ.
只因為你出生於猶太家庭，你便否認了基督。
While those born in the Christian families will deny Mohammed.
生在基督教家庭的人會否認穆罕默德。
But we do not because that’s not the truth.
但我們不會，因為那不是真理。
So you see for yourself, find out for yourself.
所以你要自己去觀察，自己去探索。
As a scientist you must keep your mind open.
身為科學家，你必須保持開放的心態。
I want you to expose to the science of God.
我想讓你們認識上帝的科學。
All right?
好嗎？
So if you believe into something, then you will be sticking on to that.
所以，因為你相信某件事，你就一直堅持己見。
This belief is artificial, it has no proof behind it.
這種信仰是人為的，背後沒有任何證據。
But we can prove it that all of them are related to each other.
但我們可以證明它們都是相互關聯的。
You see they have made segments, that’s how they have made different religions.
你看他們劃分了區塊，這就是他們創造不同宗教的方式。
If they could put them together, then they don’t believe in one religion, do they?
如果他們能將這些區塊結合起來，那他們就不會只信仰一種宗教了，對吧？
That’s the point.
這就是重點所在。